NLRB Oral History Project Miscellaneous 5435 OH
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NLRB Oral History Project Miscellaneous
1975-1980
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
National Labor Relations Board (NLRB)
Ross, Philip
5435 OH
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Oral histories (document genres).
Transcripts of interviews with forty-eight individuals who participated in the founding and administration of the National Labor Relations Board and its predecessor, the National Labor Board (1933-1947).
8050469
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 17, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 12, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) was created in 1935 under the authority of the National Labor Relations Act (popularly known as the Wagner Act). Its purpose was to implement and administer the Wagner Act which affirmed the right of employees to organize and designate representatives for collective bargaining. Beyond the Board's Wagner Act powers, the War Labor Disputes Act of 1943 authorized the NLRB to intervene to settle wartime labor disputes which threatened to impede war production. The Labor Management Relations Act of 1947 (popularly known as the Taft-Hartley Act), as amended, defined additional practices forbidden to organized labor and limited NLRB generally to judicial and policy-making functions.
The NLRB created under the Wagner Act was preceded by two earlier Boards created by President Roosevelt. The National Labor Board was established in 1933 for the purpose of adjusting industrial disputes resulting from the president's Reemployment Agreement or approved code of fair competition under the National Industrial Recovery Act (NIRA). The Labor Board was replaced less than a year later by the first National Labor Relations Board. Both early Boards functioned through regional offices to deal with labor controversies in the field. The first NLRB ceased to function after the NIRA was declared unconstitutional in May of 1935.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of transcripts of interviews with forty-eight individuals who participated in the founding and administration of the National Labor Relations Board and its predecessor, the National Labor Board (1933-1947). The interviews were directed and designed by James A. Gross (NYSSILR, professor of labor history, law and collective bargaining) in conjunction with the research and production of his books, THE MAKING OF THE NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD, 1937-1947 (SUNY, 1974); and THE RESHAPING OF THE NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD, 1937-1947 (SUNY, 1981).
Topics discussed in these interviews include the following: 1. General issues relating to the NLRB; 2. The National Labor Board (1933-1934); 3. The "old" NLRB (pre-Wagner Act); 4. The NLRB in the Wagner Act era (1935-1947); 5. The NLRB after Taft-Hartley (post-1947); 6. Regional offices; 7. The Division of Economic Research; 8. Review, appeals and enforcement of decisions; 9. Organizations and individuals exerting external influence on the NLRB; 10. CIO-NLRB relations; 11. A.F. of L.-NLRB relations; 12. Congress and the NLRB; and 13. Smith Committee investigation of the NLRB.
Respondents who participated in this project include the following NLRB staff members: David J. Saposs (Economics Division, director); Charles Fahy (general counsel); Edwin S. Smith (Board member); J. Warren Madden (chairman); Nathan Witt (executive secretary); William J. Avrutis (attorney); Meta P. Barghausen (secretary to Board chairmen); Wallace M. Cohen (review attorney); Herbert Fuchs (review attorney supervisor); Howard Lichtenstein (review attorney); Marcel Mallet-Prevost (assistant general counsel); Benedict Wolf (administrative organizer); George Bott (trial examiner and attorney); Fannie M. Boyls (trial examiner, review attorney); Owsley Vose (appeals brief supervisor); and Ogden W. Fields (executive secretary, permanent under-secretary).
Other respondents include Ernest A. Gross (Legal Division, associate general counsel); Philip Levy (legislative assistant to Senator Robert Wagner, and legal staff); George O. Pratt (regional secretary, and chief trial examiner); A. Norman Somers (attorney); Lloyd Garrison (chairman); Milton Handler (member, and general counsel); Will Maslow (trial examiner and regional attorney); Stanley S. Surrey (Legal Division); Gerhard P. Van Arkel (general counsel, member); Ida Klaus (review attorney); Louis G. Silverberg (Division of Information, director); Ruth Weyand (Enforcement Section, staff attorney); Thomas I. Emerson (staff attorney); Estelle Frankfurter (administrative aide); George Bokat (chief counsel); Paul Herzog (chairman); Ben Golden (NY Regional Office, executive secretary); Isador Polier (review attorney); James J. Reynolds (member); and Howard W. Kleeb (field examiner). Other respondents include Howard W. Smith (congressman); Leon H. Keyserlin (legal assistant to Senator Robert Wagner); Ray R. Murdock (aide to Congressman Abe Murdock); Roger Robb (Smith Committee, associate counsel); Frank M. Kleiler (secretary to William Leiserson); Charles A. Halleck (congressman); and Lee Pressman (CIO, general counsel).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Collective bargaining -- Law and legislation -- United States; Collective bargaining -- United States -- State supervision; Employee rights -- Law and legislation -- United States; Employees, Surveillance of -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States -- State supervision; Secondary boycott -- Law and legislation -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Law and legislation -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- United States -- State supervision; Labor unions -- United States -- Corrupt practices; Labor unions -- Recognition -- United States; Labor unions -- United States -- State supervision; Unfair labor practices -- United States -- State supervision; Avrutis, William J.; Barghausen, Meta P.; Biddle, Francis, 1886-1968; Blankenhorn, Hebert; Bokat, George, 1904-1973; Bott, George; Boyls, Fannie M.; Brickman, Harry, d. 1956; Carmody, John M. q (John Michael), d 1881-1962.; Cohen, Wallace M.; Consedine, William R.; Cushman, Bernard; Denham, Robert N. (Robert Newton), 1885-1954.; Emerson, Thomas I. (Thomas Irwin), 1907-1991; Fahy, Charles, 1892-1979; Fields, Ogden W.; Frankfurter, Estelle S.; Frey, John P. (John Philip), 1871-1957; Fuchs, Herbert, 1905-1988; Garrison, Lloyd; Glaser, Herbert R.; Golden, Ben; Gross, Ernest A. (Ernest Arnold), 1906-1999; Halleck, Charles A. (Charles Abraham), 1900-1986; Handler, Milton, 1903-1998; Herzog, Paul M., 1906-1986; Hillman, Sidney, 1887-1946; Hunt, A. Bruce; Keyserling, Leon H. (Leon Hirsch), 1908-1987; Klaus, Ida; Kleeb, Howard W.; Kleiler, Frank M., 1914-; Leiserson, William; Levy, Philip; Lichtenstein, Howard; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974; Madden, J. Warren (Joseph Warren), 1890-1972; Magruder, Calvert, 1893-1968; Mallet-Prevost, Marcel; Maslow, Will; Miller, Jesse I. (Jesse Isidor), 1891-1949; Millis, Harry Alvin, 1873-1948; Moore, John D. (John Denis Joseph), 1874-1940; Murdock, Ray R.; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952; Perkins, Frances, 1880-1965; Polier, Isador; Pratt, George O., 1903-1979; Pressman, Lee, 1906-1969; Reynolds, James J., Jr.; Robb, Roger; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Rosenfarb, Joseph, d. 1955; Ross, Philip; Saposs, David J. (David Joseph), 1886-1968; Silverberg, Louis G., d. 1975; Smith, Edwin Seymour, 1891-1976; Smith, Howard Worth, 1883-1976; Somers, A. Norman; Stern, Beatrice; Surrey, Stanley S. (Stanley Sterling), 1910-; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953; Toland, Edmund M., 1898-1942; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Van Arkel, Gerhard P.; Vose, Owsley; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1877-1953; Weyand, Ruth; Witt, Nathan; Wolf, Benedict; American Federation of Labor; American Medical Association; Chamber of Commerce of the United States of America; Eagle-Picher Mining and Smelting Company; International Longshoremen's Association. Pacific Coast District; Liberty League; National Association of Manufacturers (U.S.); National Lawyers' Committee; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Education and Labor; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; United States. Congress. House. Special Committee on Un-American Activities (1938-1944); United States. Congress. House. Special Committee to Investigate the National Labor Relations Board; United States. Congress. Joint Committee on Reduction of Nonessential Federal Expenditures; United States. Congress. Senate. Committee on Education and Labor. Subcommittee on Civil Liberties; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. National Labor Board; United States. National Labor Relations Board. Division of Economic Research; United States. National Labor Relations Board. Office of the General Counsel; United States. National Labor Relations Board. Review Section; United States. National Labor Relations Board. Trial Examiners' Division; United States. National Recovery Administration; United States. Subversive Activities Control Board; United States. Supreme Court.
8050469
- William Avrutis (Box 1, Folder 1)
- (Mrs.) Meta Barghausen (Box 1, Folder 2)
- George Bokat (Box 1, Folder 3)
- George Bott (Box 1, Folder 4)
- (Miss) Fannie Boyls (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Harry Brickman (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Wallace Cohen (Box 1, Folder 7)
- William R. Consedine (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bernard Cushman (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Thomas I. Emerson (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Judge Charles Fahy (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Ogden Fields (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Miss Estelle Frankfurter (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Herbert Fuchs (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Lloyd Garrison (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Herbert Glaser (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Ben Golden (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Ernest Gross (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Milton Handler (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Paul M. Herzog (Box 1, Folder 20)
- A. Bruce Hunt (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Leon Keyserling (Box 1, Folder 22)
- (Miss) IDA Klaus (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Kleiler, Frank M. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Philip Levy (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Howard Lichtenstein (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Judge J. Warren Madden (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Marcel Mallet-Prevost (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Will Maslow (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Murdock, Ray (Box 1, Folder 30)
- George O. Pratt (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Lee Pressman (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Roger Robb (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Silverberg, Louis G. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Howard Smith (Box 1, Folder 36)
- A. Norman Somers (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Stanley Surrey (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Van Arkel, Gerhard (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Owsley Vose (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Ruth Weyand (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Nathan Witt (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Benedict Wolf (Box 1, Folder 43)
- SP-Oral History - NLRB (Gross) (Box 1, Folder 44)
- SP-Oral History - NLRB (Gross) (Box 1, Folder 45)
- SP-Oral History - NLRB (Gross) (Box 1, Folder 46)
- SP-Oral History - NLRB (Gross) - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Alvin Rockwell, Aug. 27 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Scope and Contents
  tape II
- Judge Ivan Peterson, July 29, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  tape I
- Judge Ivan Peterson, July 29, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Arthur Liff, Charles Schneider, July 25, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Arthur Liff, Charles Schneider, July 25, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Oscar Smith, July 25, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Oscar Smith, July 25, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Herbert Glaser, June 27, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Herbert Glaser, June 27, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Ogden Fields, July 28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Frank Kleicker, July 24, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Frank Kleicker, July 24, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- William Basinger, July 28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Marcel Mallet, July 28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Alvin Rockwell, August 27, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Alvin Rockwell, August 27, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Robert Kleeb, Oct. 30, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- NNFS389 (806) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  microfilm reel